Good morning. Today's דף daf is צדי דלת, tzadi dalet, 94, and
we pick up at the bottom of צדי גימל עמוד ב. tzadi
gimmel amud bet. We are still dealing with this הלכה halacha about
the blood of a חטאת chatas that splatters on a garment that
you have to go ahead and launder it in the עזרה. azara.
And yeah, we continue with this משנה mishna on the bottom of
צדי גימל עמוד ב. tzadi gimmel amud bet. ניתז על העור
עד שלא הופשט. Nitas al ha-or ad shelo hufshat. So until now
we've been talking about like what type of blood are we talking
about, what stage, before it's put on the altar, when it's fit
for the altar. Now we talk about what type of a garment
it hits. So ניתז על העור עד
שלא הופשט. nitas al ha-or ad shelo hufshat. So let's say it's
not something that's a normal garment, it's not cloth, it's actually leather,
skin of an animal that has not yet been flayed. You know,
you're going to have that obviously in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
right? You slaughter the animal, now of course remember you slaughter the
animal, blood is splashing all around or spraying all around, that's not
this הלכה halacha because it hasn't yet been caught in a כלי
שרת. kli shareis. But after it's caught in a כלי שרת, kli
shareis, you could imagine that you know, some of it splashes or
you're running to the מזבח. mizbeach. Anyway, so it hits the skin
on an animal before the animal has been flayed. So the obvious
assumption is that once the skin has been flayed, it's considered enough
of a garment, of a בגד, beged, even though it's just like
it's not even processed leather yet, you know, and certainly not worked
into a piece of clothing, but that would seem to be obvious
that this הלכה halacha would apply. But the question is before it's
been flayed at what stage is this considered like it's raw materials
to make a garment out of. So אינו טעון כיבוס, eino teun
kibus, that you do not have to launder it. משהופשט, mishehufshat, once
it's been flayed, טעון כיבוס, teun kibus, then you have to, דברי
רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. The other חידוש chiddush here in addition
to the fact that this is considered a בגד beged once it's
been flayed is that the idea of laundering is a relevant term,
right? Laundering is something we normally apply to cloth. So you might
have said maybe it needs you know, cleaning or whatever, but since
the פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah is about the בגד beged
and ויכבס, v'yichabes, to launder, so you might have thought this isn't
relevant to leather. So the point is that it is, yes Charlie.
So maybe most of them are going to be turned into garments,
but what if as I flay it I say I'm going to
turn this into a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah?
Right, or or you're going to make it into a you know,
a table or something, right. Yeah, so that's also a good point
as well, right. So what makes it a garment? We'll see. So
those are good questions. So this will get this to be developed
in the גמרא. Gemara. Now that's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. רבי
אליעזר אומר אף משהופשט אינו טעון כיבוס. Rabbi Eliezer omer af mishehufshat
eino teun kibus. Even from the time that it's, even from the
time that it's been flayed. At what stage for him? Maybe for
him it would have to be processed more. We're also ignoring the
fact that leather requires tanning and a processing and so on. And
as Charlie said who knows even what use you're going to put
it to. Okay. So that's that debate and we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara. Now the סתם משנה stam mishna continues.
אינו טעון כיבוס, Eino teun kibus, you do not have to launder
אלא מקום הדם. ela makom hadam. Number one is, this is now
the סתם משנה stam mishna talking, you only have to do it
at the exact place the blood hit, it doesn't require laundering the
entire garment. ודבר שהוא ראוי לקבל טומאה. V'davar she-hu ra'uy lekabel tumah.
It has to be a garment or some type of thing that's
fit for becoming טמא. tamei. A simple example that would not be
that is let's say it's a very tiny piece of cloth so
so small that it's not usable in any way as a garment.
Okay. וראוי לכיבוס. V'ra'uy lekibus.
And it has to be something that can be laundered. Now you
might think that that's exactly the issues around the piece of leather.
A, is it fit yet for becoming טמא tamei in terms of
its stage of processing, B, just physically is it something which laundering
makes sense. אחד הבגד ואחד השק ואחד העור. Echad habeged v'echad hasak
v'echad ha-or.
And now it continues, this applies to whether it's a garment meaning
like a cloth or a sackcloth which is not made you know
which is made out of like hair of a goat or whatever
or whether it's even leather. Okay, so to which again was sort
of implicit by both opinions before, the question was what stage of
processing of the leather. טעונין כיבוס, Teunin kibus, they have to be
laundered. והכיבוס במקום קדוש, V'hakibus bemakom kadosh, and the laundering takes place
in the עזרה azara itself. ושבירת כלי חרס במקום קדוש. V'shviras kli
cheres bemakom kadosh. Similarly, which is what we're going to get to
in the rest of this פרק, perek, the תורה Torah talks about
if you cook a חטאת chatas that if it's in a, you
cook it in a earthenware vessel, then it absorbs the tastes of
the חטאת chatas and then the next day it becomes נותר. nosar.
So what are you supposed to do? So you know this is
where we get some of the הלכות halachos about כלים keilim from.
So we go ahead and, you can't get it out of the
earthenware vessel, so you have to destroy it, break it. But that
breaking also has to happen in a holy place because it still
is from the חטאת. chatas. You're not allowed to remove it from
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ומריקה
ושטיפה בכלי נחושת במקום קדוש. V'mrika v'shtifa bichlei nechoshes bemakom kadosh. So
again these are these are now the הלכות halachos where we're beginning
to transition from the blood of the חטאת chatas to the הלכות
halachos of cooking the חטאת. chatas. So the scalding and the rinsing
of a metal vessel, of a copper vessel, you don't have to
there destroy it, you can actually get the taste out. This is
like the idea of kashering. Okay, we'll see there's some special things
that are special rituals because it's a חטאת, chatas, not not just
the laws of kashering. But anyway also that has to be in
a holy place in the עזרה. azara. זה חומר בחטאת מקדשי קדשים.
Ze chomer b'chatas mikodshei kodashim. And this, the הלכה halacha of the
blood, is more stringent about a חטאת. chatas. than other קרבנות, korbanot,
because we're going to see that the other הלכות, halachot, for example,
about the cooking and the vessels, applies to also the other קרבנות
korbanot as well, but this הלכה halacha of the blood only applies
to a חטאת. chatas. Okay, nice little summary. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי, manani mili, where's this from?
Is there an אשם asham also then?
No, this פסוק pasuk about the blood? No, that's just a חטאת,
chatas, right. I mean it is an interesting question about that first
opinion, who is it? רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that makes a חטאת
chatas like an אשם asham way in the beginning and he usually
pops up and we also had his position about bringing from the
blood of a חטאת chatas into the קודש, Kodesh, whether that, you
know, invalidates the חטאת, chatas, does that also apply to an אשם?
asham? So would he say the same thing here about the blood
of a חטאת chatas and the laundering? That's a good question. Yeah,
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I don't know, that's a good question. Okay,
מנא הני מילי, manani mili, where do you get this thing from,
this issue around the leather and this debate around the leather?
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. בגד, beged, a garment. אין
לי אלא בגד מנין לרבות עור משהושט? ein li ela beged, minayin
l'rabot or mishe'hufshat? How do you know even something like a leather
once it's been flayed, which is not a garment in the sense
that it's like not woven or something? And also as רש"י Rashi
points out, who even knows what you're going to do with it?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אשר יזה עליה. asher yizeh aleha. Okay, and
so we sort of bracket the word בגד, beged, we read the
end of the verse it says anything that it's splattered on, תכבס,
techabbes, you should go launder. יכול שאני מרבה בעור עד שלא הופשט,
yachol sh'ani m'rabeh b'or ad shelo hufshat, maybe if that's true, anything
it splatters on, maybe even before the leather has been flayed? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says בגד. beged. מה בגד דבר הראוי
לקבל טומאה אף כל הראוי לקבל טומאה, ma beged davar ha'raui l'kabbel
tumah, af kol ha'raui l'kabbel tumah, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
So the sort of the expansion, it's sort of like a פרט
וכלל, prat u'klal, but
it's some type of a balance between those two words, sort of
like a מיעוט וריבוי. mi'at v'ribui. Anyway, so the concept of בגד
beged expanded, it's not limited to a בגד, beged, it's limited to
anything that is fit for becoming טמא. tamei. Now if that's true,
you
don't need the concept of garment at all. What would you say
if it like splattered on a table? Right,
that's fit for becoming טמא, tamei, it doesn't have to fit the
category of garment. So we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara
that that's going to be a little bit different because that's something
that you don't actually launder, you just like scrape it off. But
that has to do with the material. You know, if I've got
something that like you can launder that's not, I don't know, I've
got a couch that's got, you know, that's got a, you know,
what do you call it, right? That's, it's not exactly a garment
but it's, it gets absorbed into the material of the couch, right?
So anyway, so that seems to be yes, we are expanding it
to all things that can become טמא, tamei, doesn't have to be
defined as a בגד. beged. Okay, but it has to be able
to be ראוי, raui, fit to become טמא. tamei. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says בגד אין לי אלא
בגד מנין לרבות שק, beged ein li ela beged, minayin l'rabot sak,
how do I know to include a sackcloth? וכל מיני בגדים, v'chol
minei begadim, all types of בגדים? begadim? תלמוד לומר אשר עליה יזה
תכבס, Talmud lomar asher aleha yizeh techabbes,
similar,
looking at the end of the verse. יכול שאני מרבה בעור משהושט,
yachol sh'ani m'rabeh b'or mishe'hufshat,
maybe I'll even include leather after it's been flayed? תלמוד לומר בגד.
Talmud lomar beged. מה בגד דבר מקבל טומאה אף כל דבר מקבל
טומאה. ma beged davar m'kabbel tumah, af kol davar m'kabbel tumah.
No, it has to be able to, it has to be מקבל
טומאה. m'kabbel tumah. Now it sounds just exactly the same as the
previous one, but the difference is the one word, ראוי לקבל טומאה
raui l'kabbel tumah as opposed to מקבל טומאה. m'kabbel tumah. So ראוי,
raui, fit to, suggests that it's not maybe yet able to be
מקבל טומאה, m'kabbel tumah,
it's fit to, like, you know, maybe some final stage is needed,
but it's in the, but as opposed to מקבל טומאה m'kabbel tumah
which means right now it's מקבל טומאה. m'kabbel tumah. And somehow this
issue of flayed leather for is exactly the point of debate. Now
what exactly is it about? So the way רש"י Rashi explains, I
mean the גמרא Gemara is going to ask about it in a
minute for other examples, but the way רש"י Rashi explains the difference
is like this: leather after it's been flayed is
requires one more thing to be considered fit to be, to be
able to be מקבל טומאה, m'kabbel tumah, which is that you have
to have your, your intention in order to use it in the
state that it is. Because, you know, this leather, you could do
a lot of things with it, you could still want to cut
it and shape it and do עיבוד, ibbud, you know, do tanning.
I mean there's a long תוספות Tosafot discusses this issue about, really,
leather can be מקבל טומאה m'kabbel tumah before it's gone through a
process of tanning and processing? I mean who uses, now you could
use a raw piece of leather, you know, as a type of
a like a floor rug or something like that, as a throw
rug, you know, maybe even without a process of tanning, you probably
still have to scrape it and remove all like whatever. But anyway,
so it's a pretty, this is a little surprising in general because
in general we normally think that leather to be in a state
to be מקבל טומאה m'kabbel tumah has a, needs a little more
processing. But the way רש"י Rashi explains the debate, the only difference
and the language, you know, might also have suggested that the second
position here, the רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position, more requires it to
be similar to a בגד beged because he emphasizes the word בגד.
beged. But the way in the end רש"י Rashi explains it and
what's going to emerge from the גמרא, Gemara, although again it's a
little question like you'll see the גמרא Gemara is a little funny,
but is this issue about something that
physically is ready to be מקבל טומאה, m'kabbel tumah, so it's ראוי,
raui, but it's not yet מקבל טומאה m'kabbel tumah because it's lacking
your intent to use it in this state. And if you intend
to sort of wait or do more processing
it's
lacking your מחשבה, machshava, your intent to use it in some in
this state. And that's what we're going to say the debate is
with this leather that has been flayed, but not every flayed leather
is yet ready to be used as a vessel, as a type
of a thing, right, only in the so that requires the one
thing it lacks is your intent. Yes. Yeah.
I mean nobody uses raw leather for anything.
Even for a throw rug?
No, I mean you still have to I mean otherwise it'll decay,
it'll stink.
Well, is it just about scraping the stuff off of it or
is it even or is it about processing the leather itself?
There has to be at least a little bit of processing.
Yeah. So I don't know. I mean that's what תוספות Tosfos asks.
I also would have assumed that that that
and you know in general we tend to assume that until stuff
the leather is processed it's not fit for use.
And how it's processed depends I mean the processing
when you see all of those examples of like you know about
like in the Native Indians in the tipis with their leather on
the floor, you know, the sort of like you know that was
after it was flayed from the animal they would it would get
processed.
Yeah, I don't know enough about that that's great.
Anyway, okay so let's take a look so the גמרא's Gemara going
to look for other examples of something that physically is ready to
be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah but הלכתית halachically is not yet מקבל
טומאה mekabel tumah because it lacks the proper מחשבה. machshava. Yes.
Is this the same thing of if a בגד beged is sort
of like a כלי, kli, is that what רש"י Rashi says? So
it's the same גמרא, Gemara, has to be גמר מלאכה gmar melacha
or something?
Right exactly, yes for those who have learned כלים Keilim it is
in the category of גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. That is correct. Okay
and the interesting thing is that we are seeming to move away
from this concept of as we're going to see from this concept
of a garment, it could be like a rug, it could be
whatever, okay and then the question is so what if this blood
hits a you know hits my cup you know you know so
or you know so we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? So again רש"י Rashi asks it's
a funny מאי בינייהו. mai beinaihu. What do you mean מאי בינייהו?
mai beinaihu? What's בינייהו? beinaihu? Is this leather after it's been flayed?
But like the גמרא's Gemara question is sort of like give some
give me some other examples of something in this category that is
like physically you know as Chanan correctly introduces the phrase גמר מלאכה
gmar melacha or could be גמר מלאכה gmar melacha but it's dependent
on your מחשבה. machshava. It's not yet considered done because it lacks
your מחשבה machshava to declare that this is sufficiently done okay because
some things you know when they're at a stage of processing it
doesn't it's not about מחשבה machshava just objectively it's it's מקבל טומאה
mekabel tumah but this it it really depends on whether you have
decided to use it at this stage or not. So what's another
example about that? מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? אמר אביי מטלית פחותה משלוש
איכא בינייהו. Amar Abaye matlit p'chuta mishalosh ika beinaihu. If you have
a little type of a patch of of a and we're not
no longer dealing with leather we're looking at other examples a little
type of a cloth patch okay so it's small it's less than
three finger widths by three finger widths so normally if something is
that small it's not considered to be fit to be used. But
if I've got a small enough tear in my בגד, beged, I
would want to use that as a patch to sew over my
בגד. beged. So what will determine whether or not that is מקבל
טומאה mekabel tumah is whether I intend to use it for that
purpose or not. Okay. מאן דאמר ראוי הא נמי ראוי. Man d'amar
rauy ha nami rauy. This is considered physically fit to be able
to be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah דאי בעי חשיב עליה de'ibaye chashiv
alei because if you intend to use it as a patch it
will be in that category but right now if something טמא tameh
were to touch it it would not be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
it would not be טמא tameh because you have not yet had
that intent. מאן דאמר דבר המקבל טומאה Man d'amar davar hamekabel tumah
it have to actually be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah הא מיהא לאו
בר קבולי טומאה היא ha miha lav bar kibulei tumah hi it's
not yet מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because you haven't had that intent.
And we're going to go a list of things that physically could
be if you had the right מחשבה. machshava. It's not objectively in
a state where any normal person would use it as such that
doesn't require מחשבה. machshava. It's in a state where if that's your
intent then we'll say that it's מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah but it's
lacking your intent.
Okay, רבא אמר Rava amar רבא Rava says בגד שחישב עליו לצורה
איכא בינייהו. beged shechishav alav litzura ika beinaihu. I'll give you an
example of something that is finished but what's getting in the way
of it being considered מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah is your intent is
that you are the one holding off you know in the case
of the little patch you could speed up its entering into the
world of קבלת טומאה kabbalat tumah by saying I'm ready to use
it even though it's only this tiny. But sometimes your thought is
holding it back from that world. Here you were, you made this
gorgeous shirt, okay but normally any under other normal circumstance this would
be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah but you want to wait to embroider
something on the shirt. So as far as you're concerned the shirt
isn't done yet. So now it's your מחשבה machshava is getting in
the way. But nevertheless we're in a similar situation physically it's it's
able to be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah it's ראוי rauy but it's
not yet מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because your טומאה tumah your thought
is holding it back from being considered to be complete. Okay. שחישב
עליו לצורה איכא בינייהו. shechishav alav litzura ika beinaihu. מאן דאמר ראוי
הא נמי ראוי Man d'amar rauy ha nami rauy this is fit
in the sense of physically fit דאי בעי מבטל ליה למחשבתיה de'ibaye
mevatel lei lemachshavtei Say, you could, all you had to do is
decide, you know what? Forget the embroidering, and then poof, now it'll
be able to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Okay. ומאן דאמר u'man
d'amar דבר מקבל טומאה, davar mekabel tumah, it has to actively be
מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. השתא מיהא לאו בת קיבולי טומאה, hashta miha
lav bat kibulei tumah, now it is not yet in that state.
He.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, so the, one of these, or whatever איכא
דאמרי רבא אמר, ika d'amrei Rava amar, because רבא Rava was just
אמר amar a second ago. Anyway, עוצבא דחשיב עליה לקוצצה, utzpa d'chashiv
aleih lekutzatzah, איכא בינייהו. ika beinaihu. We're talking about some type of
a, like I said, like a floor mat, okay, that you have
thought about it to, you know, that you're going... so now as
a floor mat actually it is considered fit to be מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah. Okay, we're now presumably... so the only thing is that
you are, you know... it could either be a piece of leather,
it could be like a rug, okay, but you know, it's a
little jagged at the edges and so on. Maybe if it's this
leather that you just flayed and it's fit to be used as
a floor mat, but you've decided you want to trim it. It's
similar to the other example about making the embroidered garment. If you
haven't decided you wanted to trim it, it would objectively be considered
to be in a state of a floor mat and be able
to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Okay. מאן דאמר ראוי הנמי ראויה,
man d'amar rauy hanami rauyah, so it's fit. מאן דאמר דבר מקבל
טומאה הלאו מקבל טומאה עד דמקוצץ ליה. man d'amar davar mekabel tumah
halav mekabel tumah ad d'mekutzatz lei. Since you've intended to trim it,
it's not going to be מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah until you trim
it. That's a little bit different because here it sounds like you
need another physical act of trimming it, where really it should have
said what it said before, which is that you could have just
decided you no longer need to trim it and then that would
have been okay. Okay, so רש״י Rashi sort of throws that in.
So you've yet to trim it or decide you don't need to
trim it. Okay. והתניא, ve-hatanya, and we taught similarly in a ברייתא.
Baraita. התניא hatanya sometimes is a support, not a challenge. רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא אומר עוצבא שחשב עליה לקוצצה טהורה עד שיקוצצנה. Rabbi Shimon
ben Menasya omer utzpa she-chishav aleih lekutzatzah tehorah ad she-yekutzatzennah. So your
intent to trim it holds back until you're going to be ready
to trim. So that was a series of examples. So now we
have framed the debate. Again, it's pretty funny because normally you would
think leather needs a certain degree of tanning. But we have framed
the debate to be about something that physically is fit to be
מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah but not yet able because your thought is
getting in the way. Okay. אין טעון כיבוס. ein taun kibus. Now
the only thing that needs it is, okay, something that is, what
do you call it? What does the משנה Mishnah say?
Oh, it has to be ראוי לקבל טומאה. rauy lekabel tumah. Oh,
it's only the place where the blood hit, not the entire thing.
And it has to be ראוי לקבל טומאה rauy lekabel tumah and
fit to be laundered. So let's talk about those three criteria, or
those two criteria. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? First of all,
how do you know you only do it at the place the
blood hit? דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabanan, יכול ניתז על מקצת בגד יהא
כל הבגד טעון כיבוס, yachol nitaz al mikzat beged yehei kol ha-beged
taun kibus, maybe if it was on a part of the garment
you have to do the whole garment? תלמוד לומר אשר יזה עליה
תכבס. talmud lomar asher yizeh aleiha techabbes. So אשר יזה, asher yizeh,
we could read it mean the entire garment on which the blood
hit you have to launder the entire garment. But we're reading it
as אשר יזה, asher yizeh, like the place where the blood splattered,
that's what you have to launder. לא אמרתי לך אלא מקום דם
בלבד, lo amarti lecha ela mekom dam bilvad, only where the blood
is. דבר שהוא ראוי לקבל טומאה. davar she-hu rauy lekabel tumah. Now
it has to be something fit to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah.
So the
גמרא Gemara says, סתמא כרבי יהודה. stama k'Rabbi Yehuda. ראוי. rauy. Okay.
סתם Stam is like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because it didn't say
דבר המקבל טומאה. davar ha-mekabel tumah. Now we've learned that there's a
subtle difference. The difference between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is actively מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah or ראוי, rauy, fit,
if you just have the right intention. So since the משנה Mishnah
used the phrase ראוי, rauy, which suggests not yet able to be
מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, that's like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about this
leather before, after you flayed it, even though you have not yet,
you know, had the intention to make it considered done.
Okay, now, so what happens if the blood gets on it and
the person hasn't decided what it has?
So then it depends if... so again, certain things they're considered objectively
normal people would use it at this stage and then it doesn't
require your מחשבה. machshava. Things that normally people aren't don't aren't yet
ready to use at this stage, then it depends, then you need
your מחשבה machshava to make it fit to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah. Okay, so when it's in a black and white sort of
location, you know, then your מחשבה machshava is not relevant. If it's
in a gray zone, that's where your מחשבה machshava determines like which
side it falls on.
You mean to say if you're using it, then that...
Yeah, well, using it sort of constitutes your מחשבה, machshava, you know.
You don't have to constantly say, 'I hereby whatever.' Your using it
is a reflection of the fact that you now consider it to
be used. That is correct. Okay, but we're not necessarily, that's not
necessarily the case. The case is this leather is sitting around, whatever
it is.
Okay, now ראוי לכיבוס. rauy le-kibus. It has to be fit to
be laundered. למעוטי כלי דבר גרידה הוא, l'mautei kli de-bar gerida hu,
to exclude a case where it hit my mug. 'Cause that's something
what you scrape it off, you don't launder it off. Okay, so
that actually would be excluded from this הלכה halacha even though it's
a כלי, kli, even though it's מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Okay. אחד
בגד ואחד שק, echad beged ve-echad sak, whether a whether like a
garment or a sackcloth. Okay, so...
ואחד
עור, ve-echad or, and whether it is leather. So now we're going
to go back to the leather and look at it not from
this perspective of מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah.
Let's forget that whole issue. How what stage of the tanning and
of your planning, tanning and planning, anyway, it is. You know, fine,
fine, you got your you got yourself a wonderful gorgeous leather... leather
jacket. Nobody has a question that it's מקבל טומאה. Mekabel Tuma. Now
we got another problem though, because one of the criteria is that
it has to be fit for laundering. You know, do you launder
a leather garment? Is that the phrase you use? Meaning maybe you
put a little water on it and you sort of scrape off
the blood, but if we've excluded when it hits my table and
it hits my mug that I go ahead and I scrape it
off, I don't launder it off, how does the concept of laundering
apply to leather? That's our question now. Okay. So למימרא דאור בר
כיבוס הוא, Lemeimra de'or bar kibus hu, are you telling me leather
is something where the concept of laundering is a meaningful concept? רמינהו,
Reminehu, I'll ask you on this. And now we're going to look
at a discussion about שבת, Shabbos, cause there's a איסור Issur on
שבת Shabbos of laundering. Okay, here's a very here's a good הלכה,
Halacha, okay. You're not allowed to, if it's so funny how people
don't know this הלכה, Halacha, you know whatever. I see people, very
פרום Frum people sometimes, you know something hits their shirt. Totally! Yeah,
at a סעודה, Seudah, all of a sudden they take some seltzer,
they go like this or whatever. I know, I know what to
do, right?
See, we're an educated crowd, we know this.
I'm very impressed, all you guys, excellent. Okay, anyway, so okay, so
now I got a question. So you all know that if little
wine or whatever hits your shirt, you can't go ahead and do
this with water. Now let's say a little bit of wine hits
your glasses. Are you allowed to wipe it off your glasses?
You have to see, of course.
Oh, I forgot you have to see. The answer is yes. That's
not laundering. That's just on a hard surface. You can go ahead
and just wipe something off a hard surface. Let's say I got
some mud on my nice leather shoes. Okay, okay, if I got
some mud on my sneakers, which is like a fabric and it
gets absorbed, right? I can't go ahead and put water on my
fabric sneakers and get the mud out. Let's say I got it
on the surface of my nice leather shoes. What do you think?
Can I go ahead and scrape it off and use some water
and get it off?
Depends if it's polished.
Well, that's this question. But I'm asking you what do you think
the הלכה Halacha is?
I don't know. What's it going to do? It might depend what
kind of leather it is because some leather is more absorbent, some
leather is waterproof leather.
All right, okay, good answer. Let's take a look, let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so is leather something in which laundering
applies?
But isn't there something you're supposed to טובל Tovel it in a
מקוה Mikvah too if it gets טמא? Tamei?
What?
What do you mean? What?
I don't understand, what? If I put something leather in a מקוה,
Mikvah, won't it get ruined? Might be. I mean, how are you
supposed to, that's like a
separate conversation, like how
are you supposed to, but let's say you've got, so what?
But whatever,
that's a separate
conversation, like the whole question about what are you supposed to do
with like a what do you call it, a toaster, you know?
Do you have to put it in a מקוה Mikvah when you
buy a new toaster? So there's a whole lot of שיטות. Shitos.
Well, if it gets ruined, you don't have to, but anyway, somebody,
I know a certain rabbi says, yeah, I do it, I put
it in the מקוה, Mikvah, I let it sit out for 24
hours, dries out, it's fine. Anyway, whatever. Okay, moving on. Anyway, but
whether it's going to get ruined if you put it in a
מקוה Mikvah is a different conversation. All right, למימרא דאור... Lemeimra de'or...
all right, let's move on. Launder.
Then you put water on it. That's I'd say maybe הלכה. Halacha.
Fine, fine, למימרא דאור בר כיבוס הוא. Lemeimra de'or bar kibus hu.
This suggests that leather is something in which laundering is a relevant
concept. רמינהו, Reminehu, I'll ask you on this. היתה עליו לשלשת. Haysa
alav lishleshet. Let's say you've got on your garment a little like
something of spoiling thing, I mean תוספות Tosafot says basically it means
a little bit of like manure or something like that. Okay, like
a chicken manure or something. Anyway, מקנחה בסמרטוט. Mekanacha bismartut. You go
ahead and you wipe it away with a cloth. היתה של עור.
Haysa shel or. Now let's say the garment or על של עור
al shel or whatever it was on a leather garment. So נותן
עליהם מים. noten aleihem mayim. You can even use water. So obviously
you can get stuff off if you just, you know, use a
rag to get it off, you're not using water, that's not laundering.
But if it's on a leather garment, you can even use water
because that's presumably not laundering. Okay, עד שתכלה Ad shetichle until you
completely get it off. So there it seems like you can put
a lot of water on a leather garment, it's not a problem,
it's not considered laundering for שבת. Shabbos. So if it's not considered
laundering for שבת, Shabbos, how does it require laundering by this case
of a blood of a חטאת? Chatas? It should sort of be
like, you know, hitting my mug. It should be, you know, if
it's not relevant for laundering, this הלכה Halacha doesn't apply. אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. So אביי Abaye says, לא קשיא. Lo kashya. It's not
difficult. הא רבנן הא אחרים. Ha Rabbanan ha Acheirim. Whether the concept
of laundering applies to leather... let's hold off a second. It's the
debate of the רבנים Rabbonim and others. דתניא, Detanya, we learned a
ברייתא. Baraisa. הבגד והשק מכבסו. Habeged vehasak mechabso.
So here exactly it's going to be a debate about this הלכה
Halacha of the blood of a חטאת, Chatas, does it apply to
leather things? So you have a garment or a sackcloth, launder it.
הכלי והעור, Hakli veha'or, if it's some if it's like a vessel,
you know, a fork, a table, a mug, or something leather, מגררו,
megarero, just scrape it off. Okay, it's not in the category of
laundering. That's consistent with what we taught about שבת. Shabbos. אחרים אומרים,
Acheirim omrim, others say הבגד והשק והעור מכבסו. Habeged vehasak veha'or mechabso.
They put leather in the laundering side of the column. That does
require laundering by the blood. והכלי מגררו. Vehakli megarero. But if it's
some other type of a vessel like again, something of wood or,
you know, or metal or something like that, then just scrape it
off. So now what we're saying is that there's a debate whether
the concept of laundering is relevant. I mean, everybody agrees physically you
can put water on it, but would you call that laundering or
would you call it getting it wet? And then if it gets
so much into it, would you call it ruining it? Or would
you call it laundering? So we're saying that that's actually the... debate
and presumably there would be a נפקא מינה nafkamina for the הלכה
halakha of blood and there would be a נפקא מינה nafkamina for
שבת Shabbos whether you're allowed to put water on your muddy shoes.
So let's take a look. כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבי חייא בר
אשי, Keman azla ha de'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi, how does it
go like this which רבי חייא בר אשי Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi
said? זימנין סגיאין הוינא קאימנא קמיה דרב, Zimnin sagi'in havina kaimna kammai
deRav, many times I was in front of רב, Rav, ושחשי ליה
מסאני במיא, veshachshi lei masanei bemaya, and his shoes got dirty on
שבת Shabbos and he would go ahead and he would basically rub
them with water in order to clean them off. There you go,
רב Rav used water to clean off his muddy shoes. So you
see that water—it is not considered
laundering by leather. So the Gemara says כמאן כרבנן, Keman kerabbanan, that's
like the Rabbis who argue on אחרים. Acherim. So now we're making
it a debate, is leather laundering relevant? There's רבנן Rabbanan that say
that it is not laundering and you don't have to worry about
the blood thing and you don't have to worry about the שבת
Shabbos thing and then there's אחרים Acherim that says no laundering is
a relevant concept by leather and therefore it is an issue with
the blood, it is an issue with שבת. Shabbos. Now we're eventually
going to get to the issue about maybe it depends on what
type of leather. So hold on, we're not done.
So the Gemara then says like this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, ומי איכא למאן דאמר עור לאו בר חיבוץ הוא, umi
ika leman de'amar or lav bar chibbutz hu, is there really anybody
that says that laundering is not relevant by leather? One minute, it's
a
פסוק. passuk. והכתיב, vehakitiv, והבגד או השתי או הערב או כל כלי
העור אשר תכבס. vehabeged o hasheti o ha'erev o kol keli ha'or
asher techabbes. Is it תכבס? techabbes? Michael, תכבס? techabbes? Okay, אלא ela
anyway that is laundered, okay, and that's so in the whole context
about, what do you call it, about צרעת, tzara'at, right? Pretty sure
that's the פסוק. passuk. Anyway, so it uses explicitly, yeah, this is
the פסוק passuk about צרעת. tzara'at. Anyway, so it is—you see that
it is a—you got the פסוק passuk there: והבגד או השתי או
הערב או
כל כלי עץ או בגד או עור או שק כל כלי אשר
יעשה מלאכה בהם במים יובא וטמא עד הערב.
Vehabeged o hasheti o ha'erev o kol keli etz
o beged
o or o sak kol keli asher ye'aseh melakha bahem bamayim yuva
vetame ad ha'erev.
No,
but that's a different פסוק. passuk. That's not the פסוק passuk that
we just quoted. That's a different פסוק passuk with עור. or.
והבגד או השתי או הערב וכל כלי
עור אשר תכבס.
Vehabeged o hasheti o ha'erev vechol keli
or asher techabbes.
Yeah, where is it?
ויקרא י"ג נ"ח. Vayikra yud gimmel nun chet.
ויקרא Vayikra what? 58.
ויקרא י"ג נ"ח. Vayikra yud gimmel nun chet. וסר מהם הנגע וכבס
שנית
וטהר.
vesar mehem hanaga vechubbas
shenit vetaher.
Just show me here, וסר מהם הנגע.
vesar mehem hanaga.
ויקרא Vayikra one more time, י"ג yud gimmel what? נ"ח. nun chet.
I got it. והבגד או השתי או הערב או כל כלי
העור אשר תכבס,
Vehabeged o hasheti o ha'erev
o kol
keli
ha'or asher techabbes, or is it תכבס? techabbes? וסר מהם
הנגע וכבס שנית וטהר. vesar mehem hanaga vechubbas shenit vetaher. So it's
about צרעת, tzara'at, you launder them and then if the צרעת tzara'at
goes away, then they become טהור. tahor. Fine. So you see explicitly
it uses the verb to launder by, what do you call it,
by leather garments or by leather so by leather vessels. So it's
a מפורש פסוק. meforesh passuk. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, so you can't say that there's no concept of laundering
by leather.
אלא אמר רבא קרא ומתניתין ברכין. Ela amar Rava kara umatnitin berakin.
Okay, look, if it's soft leather and then the which presumably that
means two things, it means number one the stain gets inside and
it also means that the water can get inside to remove the
stain that got inside, right there laundering is a meaningful concept and
everybody would agree that laundering would apply. So when the פסוק passuk
is talking about this case about the
צרעת, tzara'at, that's talking about a soft leather. When our משנה mishnah
assumes that the הלכה halakha of blood and laundering applies to leather,
it's soft leather. By hard leather, that's where you saw this debate
of whether this הלכה halakha of blood applies to hard leather or
not, okay? And yes, the הלכה halakha would still be we would
say that by hard leather there's not a שבת Shabbos problem. By
hard leather we can see that that's where there's a debate. We
would side with the position that says there's not a שבת Shabbos
problem, but by soft leather everybody would agree that laundering is relevant.
Okay, so let's read that
again. קרא ומתניתין, kara umatnitin, the פסוק passuk and our משנה mishnah
that says that it does apply, whether it's צרעת tzara'at or the
blood, ברכין berakin is by soft leather. כי פליגי בקשין, ki pligi
bekhashin, the debate that we quoted before about the blood issue, that's
hard leather, and that also would be the שבת Shabbos position would
be that it doesn't apply to hard leather. והאמר רב חייא זימנין
סגיאין הוינא קאימנא קמיה דרב ושחשי ליה מסאני במיא. veha'amar Rav Chiyya
zimnin sagi'in havina kaimna kammai deRav veshachshi lei masanei bemaya. So what
about this הלכה halakha that he would do it on שבת Shabbos
if you're saying that that's a debate? So the Gemara says fine,
בקשין וכרבנן. bekhashin vecherabbanan. Yes, the שבת Shabbos issue is debated if
it's hard leather. If it's soft leather, everybody agrees laundering is an
issue and it falls into this category of צרעת tzara'at and the
blood, etc. Hard leather is a debate, and the position that we
allow it on שבת Shabbos would be talking about hard leather and
side with the opinion that laundering is not relevant to hard leather,
to hard leather.
Okay, so now the Gemara says like this, we're not done yet.
הדר אמר רבא, Hadar amar Rava, then says רבא, Rava, לאו מילתא
היא דאמרי. lav milta hi de'amari. You know what? Forget what I
said. It was nonsense. It was not correct. ניקו ונימא ליה לקרא.
neiku venima lei lekra. Should we get up and tell the פסוק,
passuk, דכי כתיבת ברכין כתיבת. dechi ketivat berakin ketivat. We're going to
go ahead and order around the פסוק, passuk, hey you פסוק passuk
that said that there's an idea of laundering by leather, you're only
talking about soft? I know we do it all the time. I
agree with you. Anyway, מה... ma... Who's to say the פסוק pasuk
isn't talking about a case בכלי
אחסלגייא, bicheli achsalagya, okay, with vessels of אחסלגייא, achsalagya, which is a
certain type of hard leather? I assume that your
Steinsaltz there or whatever tells you what it is. הני דמדינת הים,
Hanei demedinas hayam, we know that, you know, you get the, we
have these cases. It's so funny, all of a sudden you have
to mention hard, this special case that come from overseas, and a
minute ago we were talking about your hard leather shoes on שבת.
Shabbos. But whatever it is, anyway, who are we to say that
the פסוק pasuk is only talking about soft leather? Which is so
funny as Michael says, we say it all the time the פסוק
pasuk is talking about X and not Y. But anyway, so therefore
the פסוק pasuk has to be talking about all types of leather.
So now we got a problem, really? So laundering is relevant by
all types of leather? Wait, says רבא. Rava. וקאמר רחמנא נבעי כיבוס?
Veka'amar Rachmana nibayei kibus? And nevertheless you have to launder. אלא אמר
רבא, Ela amar Rava, so רבא Rava said, he's not going to
revise his whole point, he's just going to revise the question about
what is the פסוק pasuk by צרעת. tzara'at. The פסוק pasuk by
צרעת tzara'at applies even by hard leather. Why? He says צרעת כיון
דמגופיה קפרחה. Tzara'at keivan demigufei kapharkha.
Now this is very interesting because normally, right, exactly, normally, well although
the verb leathering doesn't, laundering doesn't apply, that's the point. So anyway,
but normally we think of צרעת tzara'at as something, you know, very
what do you call it, like you know, like miraculous or metaphysical.
On the other hand, the תורה Torah says treat it like stains,
launder it, see if it goes away, you know and so on.
So רבא Rava here is treating it very not miraculously. He says
look, somehow from within the garment itself some spot appeared. So that
shows that somehow like you know that even though it's hard leather,
something might be going on inside the garment that caused the spot
to appear. Right, normally if it's hard leather, a stain comes from
the outside, so it remains on the outside. So it's not about
laundering, it's about getting some water on it and scraping it off
and it's all very surface. Laundering is about getting in. But since
the צרעת tzara'at appeared from nowhere, presumably it came from the inside,
okay. So therefore that's where the תורה Torah actually says you got
to get the water deep in even by hard leather. Okay.
So צרעת כיון דמגופיה קפרחה, Tzara'at keivan demigufei kapharkha, since it sprouted
out from the garment itself, מחלחלי ליה ומשי ליה
רכי, mechachale lei umashyei lei rachi, you have to basically submerge it
in water, re-soften it, get the water to like you know to
penetrate inside in order to in order to do a good job.
So here basically the תורה Torah is telling you and as Michael
said yeah, you might ruin it, okay, but that's the הלכה halacha
here, so that's by the case of צרעת tzara'at I don't care
hard or soft, yes you got to go ahead and really get
the water into it. But normally, back to our point before, normally
by soft, laundering, you know,
water and laundering is relevant, and that's our משנה mishna and where
where we assume the הלכה halacha of blood applies. Hard is a
debate, is a debate, and hard there's a debate how whether laundering
is relevant, it's a debate about blood and it's a debate about
שבת Shabbos and presumably the idea of רב Rav who would clean
his shoes on שבת Shabbos whatever, assumes that hard is not a
problem by שבת. Shabbos. So we're still basically at that point. Hard
is the debate, obviously our פסק psak is where we're going in
that debate is hard is not a problem on שבת Shabbos and
it's not a laundering. Soft is where laundering is relevant. Joe, you
had a question before? No? Okay. אמר רבא אי קשיא לי הא
קשיא לי. Amar Rava i kashya li ha kashya li. If I've
got a problem here is the question I've got, כריי ופסתותי, karai
upisatosei,
let's say you're dealing with, okay, you know, pillows, okay, and and
blankets. דרקינין הנהו, derakinin hinhu, the whole point of pillows and blankets
is to be nice and soft. All right?
ותנן, utnan, and we taught היתה של עור נותנין עליה מים עד
שתכלה, hayita shel or nosin aleha mayim ad shetichle,
we talked a minute ago about this little bit of manure or
whatever, and we said if it's on a garment you can just
use a rag. If it's on leather, you can go ahead and
put on water. Okay. That was that the משנה mishna we started
with on שבת. Shabbos. People remember that? Okay. But the case was
a pillow. So what do you mean if it's leather you can
go ahead and put on water? Presumably a pillow is soft, a
soft leather. Now of course the funny thing is is that I
would not say the issue about soft versus hard is a question
about like you know whether like I mean I have a leather
like a leather couch, which is soft, you want to sit on
it, right, you don't want to be stiff. But nevertheless it's in
a way in which it's not porous. Right? I would have said
that's the difference, like how is it I mean I don't know
enough about leather but I would say it has to do like
how is it manufactured and treated in terms of whether it's porous
or not. It has less to do with whether the leather is
stiff leather or pliable leather. Okay. But anyway, but with those but
that's the question being asked. Presumably the pillow is something that is
soft and nevertheless we're saying that it's not a שבת Shabbos problem
even with soft leather to put water on it, okay. ותנן היתה
של עור נותנין עליה מים עד שתכלה. utnan hayita shel or nosin
aleha mayim ad shetichle. אלא אמר רבא כל כיבוס דלית ליה קשקוש
לא שמי כיבוס. ela amar Rava kol kibus delit lei kishkush lo
shemei kibus. You know what? When it comes to leather he's saying
all laundering, but we're going to say in a minute it means
leather. When it comes to leather, forget the soft versus the hard.
That's not the point. The point is... If you just go ahead
and put some water on leather and you scrape something off, whatever,
you know, you get a lot of water, that's not laundering. Laundering,
if if there will be laundering by leather, it's going to require
you do כסכוס, kiskus, which is like the rubbing of it together
like this. Okay. Without that, it's never going to be laundering by
the leather. So forget the hard-soft distinction. Even soft leather, okay, there
is not going to be a laundering without a type of a
rubbing together. So let's take a step back and see what we've
got.
Wait, but if I take my rag and I go like this,
you're rubbing the rag onto the leather, right?
Well, no, I mean a rubbing, no, it's not, I mean, unless
it's a real like, you know, no, like a rubbing that's getting
it off of the surface is not the rubbing we're talking about.
We're rubbing like you're sort of doing like this together in order
that really is supposed to be like getting the stuff out from
the inside. You're just rinsing, I mean you still can't put your
shoes on, right? Exactly, which is what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say. Okay. והא דאמר, Veha de’amar, לא שמיה כיבוס, lo shmei
kibus, והא דאמר רב חייא בר אשי, זימנין סגיאין, הוה קאימנא קמיה
דרב, ושחלי מסאני
במיא, Veha de’amar Rav Chiyya bar Ashi zimnin sagi’in hava ka’imna kammai
deRav v’shachlei masanei b’maya. and he basically would like, you know, rub
his shoes with water on שבת. Shabbat. שכשך? shichshoch? In. That's like
a type of a rubbing, okay, a normal type of a. How
does the English translate שכשך? shichshoch? Rubbing? I mean, do they use
different verbs there? Rinsing. Rinsing. All right, but I think rinsing also
can actually be, it's you know it means, but it can mean
like what Michael's describing, you know, it's like you're putting the water
on and you're like sort of scraping as you're putting the water
on. אבל כסכוס, aval kiskus, that should be כסכוס, kiskus, לא, lo,
but not the type of a like friction rubbing, like it's about
creating friction and whatever and really rubbing together. Okay. So basically, the
short version is yes, you can clean off your shoes on שבת,
Shabbat, your leather shoes.
Wait, and apparently also your couch.
Oh right, unless again it's in a way that the stuff got
into the pores and it's a type of a rubbing that's getting
below the surface. Exactly. Okay. אי ברכין וכדברי הכל, ei berachin uchdivrei
hakol, now we're still not giving up totally on our hard versus
soft issue, okay. We are saying that even that even by soft,
it's only going to be a problem with this rubbing, okay. So
the problem on שבת, Shabbat, so this issue about that we're going
to, I'm sorry. So שכשך, shichshoch, let me read this again. והא
דאמר veha de’amar רב חייא בר אשי Rav Chiyya bar Ashi, זימנין
סגיאין zimnin sagi’in, הוה קאימנא קמיה דרב hava ka’imna kammai deRav, ושחלי
מסאני במיא. v’shachlei masanei b’maya, שכשך shichshoch in, אבל כיבוס לא, aval
kibus lo, meaning this wasn't an answer yet, this was part of
the implicitly, when he was saying you're allowed to sort of rinse
your shoes on שבת, Shabbat, implicitly what he was telling us was
rinsing you can do it, rubbing you can't do it. Okay, so
you can't rub on שבת Shabbat with the leather. What type of
leather would that be true that you can't do this type of
a vigorous rubbing? So here's where soft versus hard makes a difference,
okay. אי ברכין וכדברי הכל, ei berachin uchdivrei hakol, soft leather, that's
where everybody would agree, so what we're doing is we're being more
lenient. Before we said by soft leather it would always be a
problem. Now we're saying by soft leather it's only a problem with
this vigorous rubbing. אי בקשין וכאחרים, ei bekashin uch’acherim, hard leather, okay,
so there, it is like אחרים acherim because for the רבנן, Rabbanan,
the רבנן Rabbanan say there's never a problem, right. So basically what
we've got is the following, I got to keep it all straight,
okay. We have like this: we've got
first we said the difference was soft and hard. We said soft
there was כיבוס, kibus, okay, and hard the רבנן Rabbanan say
no
כיבוס kibus and אחרים acherim say yes. Okay. And we assumed that
the case of the shoes was the רבנן Rabbanan and hard. Okay,
so we assumed that was the case of hard. Now because we
see that even on שבת Shabbat we allowed by the pillow or
whatever to do a type of a water, we see that even
by soft that's not always כיבוס. kibus. So what we say is
the following: is by soft, כיבוס kibus it depends. By soft if
it is
like
the type of a rubbing, okay, or the vigorous כסכוס, kiskus, right,
the vigorous rubbing, friction, you know, for whatever etc. rubbing friction etc.,
then you're going to have כיבוס, kibus, oops, כיבוס kibus
and otherwise, you know, just a sort of and other, you know,
otherwise no כיבוס. kibus. So even by soft you can you can
put water on if it's not with this friction rubbing. Hard, even
the case of the friction, okay, the rabbis would say there's no
problem. Hard, even כסכוס, kiskus, okay, even the friction type of a
thing, the rabbis say there's no problem with the leather. So what
we're saying is where. But what about אחרים? acherim? And אחרים acherim
would say that with that yes, hard is like soft, with the
כסכוס kiskus it's a problem. So כסכוס, kiskus, without כסכוס kiskus you're
not even beginning to have an issue by leather, okay. With this
vigorous rubbing, then you've got a problem by the soft and by...
So another way of looking at it is like the following. We
only begin, like the whole case is only with כשכוש. kishkus. There
is and that's then, okay, so that's without the vigorous rubbing, that's
maybe even an easier way we're saying it. Without the vigorous rubbing
it's never going to be a problem with leather, okay? With the
vigorous rubbing, by soft it will be. So if your shoes are
made out of soft leather or your couch is made out of
soft leather or whatever, it's still fine as long as you don't
do the vigorous rubbing, okay? And if you're dealing with hard leather,
then the Rabbis say even with...
So basically אחרים achairim say the same thing regardless.
אחרים achairim say soft and hard is no different, okay? But according
to the רבנן, Rabbanan, soft, you know, hard leather is never a
problem and it's soft leather combined with the כשכוש. kishkus. So basically
what we've done is we've taken this debate and we've said that
we limited it even further. Even the problem of soft is only
a problem in this case of the כשכוש, kishkus, okay?
Is there a distinction between using liquid or not when you're doing
this?
Yeah, we're assuming that this is all with liquid. Yeah, okay, so
okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says...
So let's say it was like, you know, some mud that hardened
and you want to do some vigorous rubbing to get it out,
that wouldn't be laundering at all?
Right, I think yeah, all this assumes liquid, correct.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: So basically we're
sort of what we said before, a difference between hard and soft,
except now we've added another point, that the only way you're going
to get leather to be a problem, even with soft leather, is
with combined with this כשכוש. kishkus. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אי הכי בגד נמי. Ei hachi beged nami.
So if
the
point is that you need to have the rubbing, then why by
when this little manure gets on a fabric pillow, can you only
use a שמטה? shmata? Why can't you go ahead and even use
water as long as you don't do the rubbing? If you're saying
that this rubbing is a part of the process of כיבוס. kibbus.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. בגד שרייתו זהו כיבוסו. Beged shriato
zehu kibuso. Right, by garments just water even without the vigorous rubbing
is part of the process of cleaning. Now it's an interesting question:
Does that really mean the assumption is, is that just water alone
gets a stain out? Or it could mean something different. It could
mean that by שבת Shabbos sometimes what is forbidden is things that
are part of the process even if they don't achieve yet the
end result. And since the normal way of laundering a garment is,
what do you do? You put it in the washing machine and
it fills up with water, right?
And you know, so soaking something...
But there's vigorous rubbing there too at length.
Yes, but that's my point, but the part the process begins with
a soaking in water. And since the process begins with a soaking
in water, that itself could be the דאורייתא d'oraisa even if you
haven't yet achieved the end result. So it's an interesting question what
שרייתו זהו כיבוסו shriato zehu kibuso means by, you know, by garments.
But by leather the normal process is not soaking it in water.
So by leather to the degree that there is a case, it
would require both the vigorous rubbing and the soft, right? That would
be what you would need by the leather. But by fabric even
just the water is enough. Now there is an interesting question to
sort of a little bit מלמד זכות, melamed zchus, or not really
מלמד זכות, melamed zchus, to not feel that people are doing דאורייתא
d'oraitas real דאורייתא d'oraitas all the time necessarily, is... I'm not to
say this is not at all to suggest that this is מותר,
mutar, but it's a question about whether it's an actual biblical violation.
If somebody has a little stain and they just put water on
it, is that שרייה? shria? Is that like... because the word שרייה
shria means like submerging it in water. So if they put water
on it and then they go like that and put a little
soap or put a whatever, you know, but anyway, but like okay,
but that I think you know that at least is a question
what is the degree of שרייתו. shriaso. Yeah Charlie?
Yeah,
the רש"י Rashi to that פסוק pasuk we had actually says that
כיבוס kibbus is immersion for that in that verse and he cites
תורת כהנים. Toras Kohanim.
Okay, there you go. Alright, let's just go because we eight minutes
I want to get to the משנה. Mishna. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: Okay now, רבא לטעמיה. Rava leta'ameih. רבא Rava
goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבא זרק סודר למים חייב. d'amar
Rava zarak sudar lemayim chayav. Now this, if you threw a handkerchief
into water, no soap, no rubbing, okay, presumably but it could be
that it got immersed in water and you want to get it
clean, right? You know, then you're חייב chayav on שבת. Shabbos. זרק
פשתן למים חייב. Zarak pishtan lemayim chayav. If you threw flax you're
חייב. chayav. Now בשלמא סודר עביד כיבוס. Bishlama sudar avid kibus. That
makes it laundering, like we just said, if it's a garment and
it's submerged it's laundering. אלא זרק פשתן מאי טעמא? Ella zarak pishtan
mai ta'ama? Why by flax? וכי תימא משום דמקדיח, Vechi teima mishum
demakdiach, that it basically causes it to sprout, like if you put
flax seed into water.
But this is a garment though.
Well right, אלא הכי חטי ושערי. Ella hachi chiti vesha'ari. Maybe flax
maybe means flax seeds? Okay, one גרסא girsa is זרע פשתן. zera
pishtan. אי הכי חטי ושערי נמי? Ei hachi chiti vesha'ari nami? So
it's wheat and barley as well? No. הנך אית להו... Hanach it
lehu...
No, flax seeds the problem is kneading rather...
We're getting to that. We're not up to that yet.
Okay, alright. is who רירי. riri. No, no, no. The flaxseeds, it
actually has some type of a
like strands that come out of it when they're in the water.
So what does that mean? So strands come out of it, big
deal. אי הכי Ei hachi שלחים shlachim נמי. nami.
If that's true, even this שלחים shlachim which is, which is Rashi
says, what is it? How does it translate it? שלחים? Shlachim?
What's the... I forgot...
discharges. No, no, no, after discharges.
Mucus? שלחים Shlachim are raw hides, right. Okay, I thought so. Okay,
anyway, raw hides also like stuff comes out of it when you
put it in water.
Anyway, התם Hatam קעביד ka'avid לישה. lishah. No, somehow by the case
of the flaxseed, what, what's the problem? Since when can you have
not gunk coming out of something when you put it in the
water? What's the איסור? issur? So the איסור issur is that when
somehow the flaxseed stuff comes out, it's sort of like when you
add water to flour, right, it what it does is it, the,
the change of the substance changes, has everything sort of clump together,
right? So it's sort of like somebody asked Rav Moshe Feinstein about,
or Rav Eider, about mayonnaise in tuna fish. Like he said, why
should that be an איסור issur of לישה? lishah? Normally לישה lishah
is defined like you add water to solid, to like individual pieces
of solid like flour and it makes it one big clump. So
he said, you know, so, so he said, well mayonnaise in tuna
fish, it's true it makes it all like a clump, but it
doesn't change the tuna fish pieces. It's just like a glue that
holds the tuna fish pieces together, right? As opposed to when you
add the water to the flour, it changes the pieces of the
flour and it actually makes them all, you know, some big unified
whole. So Rav Moshe was still מחמיר, machmir, which I find this
completely bizarre. So just out of deference to Rav Moshe, although I
completely don't understand it, if I have a tuna fish sandwich on
שבת, Shabbat, I sort of do it like I would have like
a, like, yeah, like spread the mayonnaise and then put the tuna
on top of it. But anyway, but that's basically what this גמרא
Gemara is saying, that you know the stuff that transforms by the
flaxseed then it all sort of becomes some homogeneous, you know, whole.
Wait, you're saying לישה lishah can occur by just throwing it in
the water?
I mean, you don't even have to... Yeah, if you just pour
water, if you pour water onto flour, you don't have to do
the act of kneading. Pouring water onto flour, pouring water onto like,
you know there's a whole issue about like also oatmeal or whatever,
and it basically takes things that are independent units and the water
transforms them, doesn't just, you know, work like glue. It transforms them
to now it becomes a homogeneous mass, that's לישה. lishah. So apparently,
apparently that's what happens by flaxseeds.
Yeah, so it even works in flax meal. I use flax meal
all the time in cooking and you put it in water and
it becomes sticky, sticks together, it's a really good binder.
Okay, there you go. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, רבא Rava expounded. מותר לכבס מינה בשבת.
Mutar lachabesh minei b'Shabbat. Like we said before. There you go. Your
shoes get dirty, right? As long as it's, if it's hard leather
and you פסקן pasken like the רבנן, Rabbanan, you can even rub
it. And if it's, and as long as you're not rubbing it,
you can certainly use water and scrape it off and whatever. Okay.
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye to רבא,
Rava, רב פפא Rav Pappa said to רבא, Rava, והא רבי חייא
בר אשי veha Rebbe Chiyya bar Ashi זימנין סגיאין zimnin sagi'in הוה
קאימנא קמיה דרב hava ka'imna kammai de-Rav שכשך להו מסאני במיא shichshech
lehu masani b'maya and he sort of rubbed his his his shoes
with water, but the שכשך shichshech is like rinsed it or whatever,
it's not this vigorous rubbing.
So שכשך אין אבוקיבוס לא, shichshech in avukivus lo, so it's only
the rinsing it's not the vigorous rubbing. So הדר אוקי רבא אמורא
עליה ודרש hadar oki Rava amora alei v'darash then he got up
and said דברים שאמרתי לפניכם טעות הם בידי devarim she'amarti lifneichem ta'ut
hem b'yadi it's a mistake. ברם כך אמרו Beram kach amru שכשך
מותר קיסכוס אסור, shichshech mutar kiskus assur, קיסכוס אסור. kiskus assur. Now
the question still is, but what's he talking about? Is he talking
about soft, קיסכוס אסור, kiskus assur, which is what we said, right,
that soft, this vigorous rubbing is forbidden? Or is he saying even
hard קיסכוס kiskus is אסור assur and he's פסקן pasken like the
אחרים Acherim and not like the רבנן? Rabbanan? So in the end
it's not clear, right, whether how we פסקן pasken this, the גמרא
Gemara isn't clear how we're coming out on the hard debate. Is
רבא'ס Rava's case the soft case or is רבא'ס Rava's case the
hard case? So the פשט pshat of this is that if your
shoes get muddy on שבת, Shabbat, you can put water on it,
you can scrape it off, but don't go ahead and like vigorously
rub it unless you figure out whether they're considered hard and how
we פסקן pasken on the hard debate. Now, by the way, I
want to read you a very important תוספות, Tosafot, right, this thing
about getting stuff wet or whatever is considered an issue on שבת
Shabbat by garments. So it's considered כיבוס. kibus. So תוספות Tosafot asks
the question, how about the fact that there's a famous גמרא Gemara
like you can walk through a river on שבת Shabbat to get
somewhere? Oh yeah. What about the fact that your garments get wet?
Why isn't that considered כיבוס? kibus? So תוספות Tosafot says well, A,
you might not be trying, but it's פסיק רישא, psik reisha, ניחא
ליה לא ניחא ליה. nicha lei lo nicha lei. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot
says a river is dirty. If the getting of it wet is
a process of getting it stained, that's not considered laundering. And therefore
if you look at the very top line of תוספות Tosafot on
our עמוד, amud, no it's the middle of a תוספות, Tosafot, very
top line of תוספות Tosafot on our עמוד amud where we are,
ולא משום שרייתן זהו כיבוסן, V'lo mishum shri'atan zehu kibusan,
why are we not concerned in the case of the river? דדרך
טינוף הוא, de-derech tinuf hu, because that way actually is a soiling
process, it's not a cleansing process. ומהאי טעמא נמי u'me'hai ta'ama nami
שרי לקנח ידו במפה בשבת. sharei l'kane'ach yado b'mapah b'Shabbat. Don't anybody
go home and after you wash your hands say, oh I can't
wipe them on a towel because I just learned in the דף
יומי Daf Yomi that when you... you get some some something cloth
wet on שבת *Shabbos*, that's considered to be laundering. So תוספות *Tosafos*
says that's only when getting it wet is part of a process
of cleaning it. If getting it wet is because your hands are
wet and they are and you know and you just went ahead
and washed your hands and therefore you're getting the towel dirty in
the process, that is not considered laundering, getting something dirty. Okay, let's
finish up to the משנה *mishna*.
Okay, how about this weather is...?
I don't know. Okay, let's finish up to the משנה *mishna*. Okay,
הקיבוס במקום קדוש *Ha'kibus b'makom kadosh*, so the laundering takes place in
a holy place. מנא הני מילי *Mina hanei mili*, where do we
know this from? דתנו רבנן *D'tanu rabanan*, as our rabbis taught: תכבס
במקום קדוש *Tichabes b'makom kadosh*. Fine, that's clear enough. שבירת כלי חרס
מנא לן *Shviras kley cheres minalan*, how do you know breaking the
pottery vessels that absorbed the חטאת *chatas*? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, וכלי
חרס אשר תבושל בו ישבר *U'kley cheres asher tuvushal bo yishaver*. Okay,
which is right after the תכבס במקום קדוש *Tichabes b'makom kadosh*,
so the juxtaposition is that it's במקום קדוש *b'makom kadosh*, right? It's
in the עזרה *azarah*. Okay. מריקה ושטיפה בכלי נחושת מנא לן *Mrika
v'shtifa b'kli nechoshes minalan*, how do you know that has to be
in a holy place? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, ואם בכלי נחושת בושלה
ומרק ושוטף במים *V'im b'kli nechoshes bushala u'marak v'shutaf bamayim*. Again, none
of that mentions a holy place, but since it's
juxtaposed to the holy place by the laundering, we assume that's in
a holy place as well. זה חומר בחטאת *Zeh chomer b'chatas*, this
is the way חטאת *chatas* is more stringent, this הלכה *halacha* about
the blood, it only applies to a חטאת *chatas*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, ותו ליכא *V'su leka*, is this the only way חטאת
*chatas* is more stringent? ואיכא שנכנס דמה לפנים *V'ika she'nichnas damah lifnim*,
how about the fact that when the blood of a חטאת *chatas*
goes into the inner sanctum it invalidates, and it's not true about
other sacrifices? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, בחטאות החיצוניות *B'chatos hachitzoniyos*, no,
we're talking about outer חטאות *chatos* within— I'm sorry, I jumped ahead.
How about the fact that there are inner such a thing as
inner חטאות *chatos*? So that's— makes a חטאת *chatas* a more weighty
קרבן *korban*, a more strict קרבן *korban* because there exists the phenomenon
of inner חטאות *chatos*. The גמרא *Gemara* says, בחטאת החיצונית *B'chatas hachitzonis*,
we're talking about outer חטאת *chatas*. But how about the הלכה *halacha*
שכן אם נכנס דמה לפנים פסולה *she'ken im nichnas damah lifnim psulah*?
Okay, but how about the weighty הלכה *halacha* of חטאת *chatas* that
if the blood goes on the inside it invalidates? That only applies
to a חטאת *chatas*. כרבי עקיבא דאמר כל דמים שנכנסו להיכל לכפר
פסולה *K'Rabbi Akiva d'amar kol damim she'nichnasu l'heichal l'chaper psulah*. Okay, so
no, Rabbi עקיבא *Akiva*, it's not limited to a חטאת *chatas*. Okay,
how about the fact that a חטאת *chatas* is weightier שכן מכפרים
על חייבי כריתות *she'ken mechaperim al chayavei krisos*, that they even— they
atone for sins of כרת *kares*, that makes a חטאת *chatas* weighty?
בחטאת שמיעת הקול *B'chatas shmiyas hakol*. Okay, we could— no, we're talking
about— there are חטאות *chatos* that aren't like that, like a חטאת
*chatas* about— about not testifying and swearing about not testifying or whatever,
so not all חטאות *chatos* have that weightiness that they atone for
כרת *kares*.
But we're just talking about קיבוס *kibus* though in our משנה *mishna*.
But we said, but we said "this is the weighty aspect regarding
what we're talking about". But we're going to get to that. שכן
טעונה ארבע מתנות *She'ken te'una arba matanos*, ah, how about the fact
that a חטאת *chatas* is weightier that you— you put on four
applications of blood? כרבי ישמעאל דאמר כל הדמים טעונים ארבע מתנות *K'Rabbi
Yishmael d'amar kol hadamim te'unim arba matanos*. Rabbi ישמעאל *Yishmael* says that
all bloods you put four applications, not the two that are four,
but four applications on the four walls. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
אל— "but how about the fact that"— ארבע קרנות *Arba kranos*, okay,
but even across Rabbi ישמעאל *Yishmael*, the four is on the walls,
the חטאת *chatas* gets put up at the corners. You could have
also said how about the הלכה *halacha* that by a חטאת *chatas*
שלא לשמה *she'lo lishma* invalidates, but maybe you would have said a
קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* is like it, that's not unique. Anyway, the
גמרא *Gemara* says, ולטעמיך *V'l'ta'ameich*, why only asking about the corners, about
the
horns? ואיכא קרן *V'ika keren*, I mean the very fact that it's
the horn at all, not just the four horns. ואיכא אצבע *V'ika
etzba*, that you use your finger. ואיכא חודה *V'ika chudah*, it's at
the— it's at the edge of the corner. אלא חד מתרי תלתא
חומרי נקט *Ela chad mitrei tlata chumrei nakat*, it's not saying all
of the ways חטאת *chatas* is stringent. This— in this thing of
blood, that's one of the ways the חטאת *chatas* is more stringent,
other ways the חטאת *chatas* is more stringent as well. Fine, יישר
כוח *shkoach*. Okay, we'll pick up with the משנה *mishna* tomorrow.